<data wiki-url="http://simile.mit.edu/shelf/" wiki-section="Texas History">

<event start="1829" title="Irish immigrants arrive in South Texas">October – The first of several large groups of Irish immigrants arrive to settle in South Texas.</event>

<event start="Apr 6 1830 00:00:00 GMT" title="Mexican government prevents legal immigration into Texas">April 6 – The Mexican government passes a law stopping legal immigration into Texas from the United States except in special cases. Relations between Anglo settlers and the Mexican government deteriorate.</event>

<event start="1831" title="German families migrate to southeastern Texas">Johann Friedrich Ernst, his wife and five children are the first German family to arrive in Texas, settling in present-day Austin County. Ernst writes a long letter to a friend in Germany describing Texas as an earthly Eden. The letter is widely circulated, persuading a small but steady stream of German families to migrate to southeastern Texas.</event>

<event start="Jun 26 1832 00:00:00 GMT" title="Mexican forces clash with Texans, causing bloodshed" end="Jun 29 1832 00:00:00 GMT 00:00:00 GMT">June 26 – The first bloodshed of the Texas Revolution takes place at Velasco when Texans, transporting a cannon from Brazoria to Anahuac, are challenged by Mexican forces at Velasco. The Mexicans surrender on June 29.</event>

<event start="Oct 2 1835 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas Revolution begins">Oct. 2 – Mexican troops attempt to retrieve a cannon that had been given to Gonzales colonists for protection from Indian attack. The skirmish that ensues as Gonzales residents dare the Mexicans to "come and take it" is considered the opening battle of the Texas Revolution.</event>

<event start="Oct 10 1835 00:00:00 GMT" title="Telegraph and Texas Register begins publication">Oct. 10 – Gail Borden begins publishing the newspaper "Telegraph and Texas Register" at San Felipe de Austin.</event>

<event start="Nov 1 1835 00:00:00 GMT" title="Delegates establish provisional government at San Felipe" end="Nov 7 1835 00:00:00 GMT 00:00:00 GMT">Nov. 1 – A "consultation" convenes at San Felipe; on Nov. 7 the delegates agree to establish a provisional government.</event>

<event start="Nov 24 1835 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas Rangers organization established by provisional government">Nov. 24 – The Texas Rangers organization is officially established by Texas" provisional government. Although Stephen F. Austin had hired 10 frontiersmen as "rangers" to help protect his colonists against Indian raids in 1823, not until 1835 was the law-enforcement group formally organized.</event>

<event start="Mar 2 1836 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas Declaration of Independence adopted">March 2 – The Texas Declaration of Independence is adopted at Washington-on-the-Brazos.</event>

<event start="Mar 6 1836 00:00:00 GMT" title="Siege of the Alamo ends with all defenders killed">March 6 – A 13-day siege of the Alamo by Mexican troops led by Gen. Antonio López de Santa Anna ends on this day with a battle in which all remaining defenders are killed.</event>

<event start="Mar 10 1836 00:00:00 GMT" title="Sam Houston retreats to avoid Mexican army">March 10 – Sam Houston abandons Gonzales and retreats eastward to avoid the advancing Mexican army. Panicky settlers in the area flee as well in an exodus called the Runaway Scrape.</event>

<event start="Mar 27 1836 00:00:00 GMT" title="350 Texas prisoners executed by order of Santa Anna">March 27 – About 350 Texan prisoners, including their commander James Fannin, are executed at Goliad by order of Santa Anna. An estimated 30 Texans escape.</event>

<event start="Apr 21 1836 00:00:00 GMT" title="Sam Houston and troops defeat the Mexican army" end="S0 00:00:00 GMT">April 21 – In a battle starting about 4:30 p.m. and lasting 18 minutes, Texan troops led by Sam Houston defeat the Mexican army commanded by Santa Anna at San Jacinto near present-day Houston. Houston reports that 630 Mexican troops were killed and 730 were taken prisoner. Of the Texas troops, nine of a force of 910 were killed or mortally wounded, and 30 were less seriously wounded.</event>

<event start="May 14 1836 00:00:00 GMT" title="Treaties of Velasco end the Texas Revolution">May 14 – Santa Anna and Texas" provisional president David Burnet sign two Treaties of Velasco – one public, the other secret – ending the Texas Revolution. The treaties were, however, violated by both sides. Texas" independence was not recognized by Mexico and Texas" boundary was not determined until the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, which ended the Mexican War, was signed in 1848.</event>

<event start="Sep 5 1836 00:00:00 GMT" title="Sam Houston becomes president of the new republic">Sept. 5 – Voters of the new republic choose their first elected officials: Sam Houston becomes president and Lorenzo de Zavala, vice president. The voters also overwhelmingly approve a referendum requesting annexation by the United States. U.S. President Martin Van Buren refuses to consider it, however, citing fear of war with Mexico and constitutional scruples.</event>

<event start="1836" title="The first Congress of the Republic of Texas convenes">Oct. – The first Congress of the Republic of Texas convenes at Columbia.</event>

<event start="1837" title="Republic of Texas officially recognized by the United States">The Republic of Texas is officially recognized by the United States, and later by France, England, the Netherlands and Belgium.</event>

<event start="Aug 1 1839 00:00:00 GMT" title="First sale of town lots in Austin is held">Aug. 1 – The first sale of town lots in the new capital of the Republic, which is named for Stephen F. Austin, is held.</event>

<event start="Mar 19 1840 00:00:00 GMT" title="Comanches killed after failed peace treaty negotiation">March 19 – Comanches, led by a dozen chiefs, meet with officials of Texas government to negotiate a peace treaty. Believing the Comanches to have reneged on a promise to release all white prisoners, the Texans take the chiefs prisoner. During the Council House fight that follows, 35 Comanches are killed, as are seven Texans.</event>

<event start="Aug 5 1840 00:00:00 GMT" title="Comaches start rampage in relatiation, defeated" end="Aug 11 1840 00:00:00 GMT 00:00:00 GMT">Aug. 5 – Near Hallettsville, a large band of Comanches, in retaliation for the Council House Fight, begin killing and looting their way across Central Texas. Texas Rangers and a volunteer army defeat the Comanches on Aug. 11 at Plum Creek near Lockhart.</event>

<event start="Jun 20 1841 00:00:00 GMT" title="Santa Fe Expedition makes its way west to solidify claims to territory">June 20 – The Santa Fé Expedition, launched without Texas Congressional authorization by Pres. Mirabeau B. Lamar, leaves Central Texas on its way west to establish trade with and solidify Texas" claims to territory around Santa Fé. Members of group are taken prisoner by Mexican troops, marched to Mexico City and imprisoned. They are finally released in 1842.</event>

<event start="1842" title="Large-scale German immigration begins">The first seeds of large-scale German immigration to Texas are sown when a German society, the Adelsverein, purchases land for settlements in Central Texas.</event>

<event start="Mar 1 1845 00:00:00 GMT" title="U.S. Congress passes resolution for annexing Texas">March 1 – U.S. Congress passes a "Joint Resolution for Annexing Texas to the United States."</event>

<event start="1845" title="Germans arrive in Central Texas">mid-March – The first of many large groups of Germans arrive in Central Texas, settling at New Braunfels.</event>

<event start="Jul 4 1845 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas Consitutional Convention accepts annexation proposal">July 4 – The Texas Constitutional Convention votes to accept the United States annexation proposal; it drafts an Annexation Ordinance and State Constitution to submit to the voters of Texas.</event>

<event start="Oct 13 1845 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas voters overwhelmingly approve annexation">Oct. 13 – Texas voters overwhelmingly approve annexation, the new state constitution and the annexation ordinance.</event>

<event start="Dec 29 1845 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas becomes 28th state">Dec. 29 – The U.S. Congress approves, and President James K. Polk signs, the "Joint Resolution for the Admission of the State of Texas into the Union." Texas becomes the 28th state.</event>

<event start="Feb 19 1846 00:00:00 GMT" title="Formal transfer of government takes place">Feb. 19 – Although Texas officially became a state on Dec. 29, 1845, the formal transfer of government does not take place until this date.</event>

<event start="May 8 1846 00:00:00 GMT" title="Battle of Palo Alto begins two-year Mexican War">May 8 – The Battle of Palo Alto near Brownsville is the first major battle of the two-year Mexican War.</event>

<event start="Feb 2 1848 00:00:00 GMT" title="Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo is signed, ending the war">Feb. 2 – The Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo is signed, ending the War with Mexico and specifying the location of the international boundary.</event>

<event start="Feb 11 1850 00:00:00 GMT" title="First railroads in Texas are chartered">Feb. 11 – The first railroad to actually begin operation in Texas is chartered by the state government. The Buffalo Bayou, Brazos and Colorado begins operation in 1853.</event>

<event start="Nov 25 1850 00:00:00 GMT" title="Compromise of 1850 signed">Nov. 25 – Texas" governor signs the Compromise of 1850, in which Texas gives up its claim to land that includes more than half of what is now New Mexico, about a third of Colorado, a corner of Kansas, the Oklahoma Panhandle, and a small portion of Wyoming in exchange for the United States" assumption of $10 million in debt; Texas keeps its public lands.</event>

<event start="1854" title="Two reservations for American Indians established">Two reservations are established for Indians in West-Central Texas: one for Comanches on the Clear Fork of the Brazos in Throckmorton County, the other for more sedentary Indian groups, such as Tawakonis, Wacos and Tonkawas, near Fort Belknap in Young County.</event>

<event start="Mar 27 1856 00:00:00 GMT" title="Col. Robert E. Lee arrives in San Antonio">March 27 – Col. Robert E. Lee arrives in San Antonio. He serves at Camp Cooper on the Comanche reservation beginning April 9. He returns to Washington for a short time, coming back to San Antonio and Fort Mason in February 1860.</event>

<event start="Apr 29 1856 00:00:00 GMT" title="Camels arrive in Indianola for U.S. Army experiment">April 29 – Fifty-three camels arrive at the port of Indianola for a U.S. Army experiment using them for pack animals in the arid areas of the Southwest. They are quartered at Camp Verde, near present-day Kerrville, and are later joined by 41 more. The experiment lasted about 10 years.</event>

<event start="Sep 15 1858 00:00:00 GMT" title="Butterfield Overland Mail crosses Texas">Sept. 15 – The southern route of the Butterfield Overland Mail crosses Texas on its way between St. Louis, Mo., and the West Coast. Service is discontinued in March 1861 with the outbreak of the Civil War and is never resumed.</event>

<event start="Jul 13 1859 00:00:00 GMT" title="Violent clashes erupt in Brownsville area">July 13 – Violent clashes between Juan "Cheno" Cortina and Anglo lawmen begin in the Brownsville area in the Lower Rio Grande Valley. Texas Rangers and federal troops eventually halt the so-called "Cortina War" in 1875.</event>

<event start="1859" title="American Indians in West-Central Texas removed by the federal government">July – Indians on the West-Central Texas reservations are moved by the federal government to reservations in Indian Territory (now Oklahoma).</event>

<event start="Feb 1 1861 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas secedes from the Union">Feb. 1 – The Secession Convention approves an ordinance withdrawing Texas from Union; the action is ratified by the voters on Feb. 23 in a referendum vote. Secession is official on March 2.</event>

<event start="Feb 13 1861 00:00:00 GMT" title="Robert E. Lee assumes command of the Confederate Army">Feb. 13 – Robert E. Lee is ordered to return to Washington from regimental headquarters at Fort Mason to assume command of the Union Army. Instead, Lee resigns his commission; he assumes command of the Confederate Army by June 1862.</event>

<event start="Mar 1 1861 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas is accepted as a state in the Confederacy">March 1 – Texas is accepted as a state by the provisional government of the Confederate States of America, even before its secession from the Union is official.</event>

<event start="Mar 5 1861 00:00:00 GMT" title="Secession Convention accepts Confederate statehood">March 5 – The Secession Convention approves an ordinance accepting Confederate statehood.</event>

<event start="Mar 16 1861 00:00:00 GMT" title="Sam Houston resigns as governor">March 16 – Sam Houston resigns as governor in protest against secession.</event>

<event start="Aug 10 1862 00:00:00 GMT" title="Confederates kill 19 Union loyalists on the Nueces River">Aug. 10 – About 68 Union loyalists, mostly German immigrants from the area of Comfort, in Central Texas, start for Mexico in an attempt to reach U.S. troops; 19 are killed by Confederates on the Nueces River. Eight others are killed on Oct. 18 at the Rio Grande. Others drown attempting to swim the river. Their deaths are commemorated in Comfort by the Treue der Union (True to the Union) monument.</event>

<event start="1862" title="42 Union sympathizers are hanged">October – Forty-two men thought to be Union sympathizers are hanged at various times during October in Gainesville.</event>

<event start="May 13 1865 00:00:00 GMT" title="Battle of Palmito Branch">May 13 – The Battle of Palmito Ranch is fought near Brownsville, after the official end of the Civil War, because word of the war"s end at Appomattox on April 9 has not yet reached troops in Texas.</event>

<event start="Jun 19 1865 00:00:00 GMT" title="Slavery is declared abolished">June 19 – Gen. Gordon Granger arrives at Galveston to announce that slavery has been abolished, an event commemorated today by the festival known as Juneteenth.</event>

<event start="1865" title="Freedmen's Bureau begins operation">Sept. – The Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen and Abandoned Lands (the Freedmen"s Bureau) begins operating in Texas, charged with helping former slaves make the transition to freedom.</event>

<event start="Mar 15 1866 00:00:00 GMT" title="Secesion Convention actions nullified">March 15 – The Constitutional Convention approves an ordinance to nullify the actions of the Secession Convention.</event>

<event start="Aug 20 1866 00:00:00 GMT" title="Proclamation of peace declared">Aug. 20 – President Andrew Johnson issues a proclamation of peace between the United States and Texas.</event>

<event start="1866" title="Cattle drives begin in earnest">Cattle drives, which had been occasional in the 1830s, sporadic during the 1840s and 1850s, and almost nonexistent during the Civil War, begin in earnest, mostly to markets and railheads in Midwest. They are at their peak for only about 20 years, until the proliferation of railroads makes them unnecessary.</event>

<event start="1867" title="Congressional Reconstruction begins" end="1870 00:00:00 GMT">1867-1870 Congressional (or Military) Reconstruction replaces Presidential Reconstruction.</event>

<event start="1868" title="Large scale irrigation begins">Large-scale irrigation begins in Texas when canals are built in the vicinity of Del Rio.</event>

<event start="Nov 30 1869 00:00:00 GMT" title="New state constitution approved">Nov. 30 – Texas voters approve a new state constitution.</event>

<event start="Mar 30 1870 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas readmitted to Congressional representation">March 30 – President Grant signs the act readmitting Texas to Congressional representation.</event>

<event start="1870" title="Edmund J. Davis becomes governor">Edmund J. Davis becomes the first Republican governor of Texas.</event>

<event start="1871" title="Massacre at Salt Creek">May – Seven men in a wagon train are massacred at Salt Creek, about 20 miles west of Jacksboro, by Kiowas and Comanches led by chiefs Satanta, Big Tree, Satank and Eagle Heart.</event>

<event start="1872" title="Construction begins on Texas &amp; Pacific Railway">Oct. – Construction begins on the Texas &amp; Pacific Railway; the 125-mile stretch between Longview and Dallas opens for service on July 1, 1873.</event>

<event start="1873" title="Buffalo Soldiers are first posted to Texas">Black "Buffalo Soldiers" are first posted to Texas, eventually serving at virtually every frontier fort in West Texas from the Rio Grande to the Panhandle, as well as in other states.</event>

<event start="1873" title="Houston and Texas Central Railway reaches the Red River">The Houston and Texas Central Railway reaches the Red River, connecting there with the Missouri, Kansas and Texas Railroad and creating the first all-rail route from Texas to St. Louis and the East.</event>

<event start="Jan 17 1874 00:00:00 GMT" title="Richard Coke becomes governor">Jan. 17 – The inauguration of Democrat Richard Coke as governor marks the end of Reconstruction in Texas.</event>

<event start="Sep 28 1874 00:00:00 GMT" title="Battle of Palo Duro Canyon">Sept. 28 – Col. Ranald Mackenzie leads the 4th U.S. Cavalry in the Battle of Palo Duro Canyon, south of present-day Amarillo, an encounter that ends with the confinement of southern Plains Indians in reservations in Indian Territory. This makes possible the wholesale settlement of the western part of the state.</event>

<event start="Feb 15 1876 00:00:00 GMT" title="Present state constitution adoped">Feb. 15 – The present state constitution is adopted.</event>

<event start="Oct 4 1876 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas A&amp;M University opens">Oct. 4 – The Agricultural and Mechanical College, later Texas A&amp;M University, opens at College Station, becoming the first public institution of higher learning in the state.</event>

<event start="1876" title="First cattle ranch established">Charles Goodnight establishes the JA Ranch in Palo Duro Canyon, the first cattle ranch located in the Panhandle.</event>

<event start="1877" title="El Paso Salt War takes place">Sept. – The El Paso Salt War is the culmination of a long dispute caused by Anglos" attempts to take over salt-mining rights at the foot of Guadalupe Peak, a traditionally Mexican-American salt source.</event>

<event start="Dec 16 1881 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas &amp; Pacific Railway reaches Sierra Blanca">Dec. 16 – The Texas &amp; Pacific Railway reaches Sierra Blanca in West Texas, about 90 miles east of El Paso.</event>

<event start="Sep 15 1883 00:00:00 GMT" title="Classes begin at the University of Texas">Sept. 15 – Classes begin at The University of Texas.</event>

<event start="1884" title="Fence-cutting made a felony">Fence-cutting wars prompt the Texas Legislature to pass a law making fence-cutting a felony.</event>

<event start="Aug 19 1886 00:00:00 GMT" title="Hurricane levels Indianola" end="Aug 21 1886 00:00:00 GMT 00:00:00 GMT">Aug. 19-21 – A hurricane destroys or damages every house in the port of Indianola, finishing the job started by another storm 11 years earlier. Indianola is never rebuilt.</event>

<event start="May 16 1888 00:00:00 GMT" title="Present state capitol dedicated">May 16 – The present state capitol is dedicated.</event>

<event start="1891" title="Railroad Comission established">The Railroad Commission, proposed by Gov. James Hogg, is established by the Texas legislature to regulate freight rates and to establish rules for railroad operations.</event>

<event start="Jun 9 1894 00:00:00 GMT" title="Oil is discovered at Corsicana">June 9 – Oil is discovered at Corsicana by workers drilling for water; a commercial field opens in 1896, becoming the first small step in Texas" rise as a major oil producer.</event>

<event start="May 16 1898 00:00:00 GMT" title="Teddy Roosevelt recruits Rough Riders for Spanish-American War">May 16 – Teddy Roosevelt arrives in San Antonio to recruit and train "Rough Riders" for the First Volunteer Cavalry to fight in the Spanish-American War in Cuba.</event>

<event start="1898" title="Texas experiences its coldest winter on record" end="1899 00:00:00 GMT">1898-1899 Texas experiences its coldest winter on record statewide.</event>

<event start="Sep 8 1900 00:00:00 GMT" title="'The Great Hurricane' destroys much of Galveston and kills 6,000">Sept. 8 – The "Great Hurricane" the greatest natural disaster in human terms ever to strike North America, destroys much of Galveston and kills 6,000 people there.</event>

<event start="Jan 10 1901 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas enters the petroleum age">Jan. 10 – A gusher drilled by mining engineer Capt. A.F. Lucas at Spindletop near Beaumont catapults Texas into the petroleum age.</event>

<event start="1902" title="The poll tax becomes a requirement.">The poll tax becomes a requirement for voting.</event>

<event start="1906" title="Texans can vote for a U.S. senator for the first time">For the first time, Texans can vote for U.S. senator in the Democratic primary. Although the Texas legislature retains ultimate appointment authority, primary voters can express their preferences. Not until 1916 are Texas voters able to directly elect U.S. senators.</event>

<event start="Mar 2 1910 00:00:00 GMT" title="Lt. Benjamin D. Foulois makes the first military air flight">March 2 – Lt. Benjamin D. Foulois makes the first military air flight in a Wright brothers plane at Fort Sam Houston in San Antonio. The seven-and-a-half-minute flight marks the shaky beginnings of U.S. Air Force.</event>

<event start="1911" title="The Mexican civil war spills across the border" end="1920 00:00:00 GMT">The Mexican civil war spills across the border, as refugees seek safety, combatants seek each other, and Texas settlements are raided for supplies by all sides in the fighting. Pancho Villa and his followers are active along the border during some of this time.</event>

<event start="1917" title="The United States participates in World War I" end="1918 00:00:00 GMT">The United States participates in World War I.</event>

<event start="1917" title="Gov. James Ferguson is impeached and convicted">Gov. James Ferguson is impeached and convicted; he leaves office.</event>

<event start="1918" title="Texas women win the right to vote">March – Texas women win the right to vote in primary elections.</event>

<event start="1918" title="Annie Webb Blanton becomes the first woman elected to a statewide office">Annie Webb Blanton becomes the first woman elected to a statewide office when she is elected State Superintendent of Public Instruction.</event>

<event start="1919" title="Gov. William P. Hobby vetoes appropriations for German Dept. of The University of Texas">Responding to anti-German sentiment, Gov. William P. Hobby vetoes appropriations for German Dept. of The University of Texas.</event>

<event start="1919" title="Texans adopt a prohibition amendment">Texans adopt a prohibition amendment to the state constitution.</event>

<event start="1920" title="Large-scale agricultural irrigation begins in the High Plains">Large-scale agricultural irrigation begins in the High Plains.</event>

<event start="1925" title="Miriam 'Ma' Ferguson becomes Texas' first woman governor">Miriam "Ma" Ferguson becomes Texas" first woman governor, serving as a figurehead for her husband, former Gov. James E. Ferguson.</event>

<event start="Sep 30 1925 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas Tech University begins classes in Lubbock as Texas Technological College">Sept. 30 – Texas Tech University begins classes in Lubbock as Texas Technological College.</event>

<event start="Jun 26 1928 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texas Tech University begins classes in Lubbock as Texas Technological College" end="Jun 29 1928 00:00:00 GMT">June 26-29 – The Democratic National Convention is held in Houston, the first nominating convention held in a Southern city since 1860.</event>

<event start="Feb 17 1929 00:00:00 GMT" title="League of United Latin American Citizens (LULAC) founded">Feb. 17 – The League of United Latin American Citizens (LULAC) is founded in Corpus Christi.</event>

<event start="Sep 5 1930 00:00:00 GMT" title="Huge East Texas oil field discovered">Sept. 5 – The Daisy Bradford #3 well, drilled near Turnertown in Rusk County by wildcatter C.M. (Dad) Joiner, blows in, heralding the discovery of the huge East Texas Oil Field.</event>

<event start="1935" title="State's prohibition law repealed">Two years after federal prohibition was repealed, Texas voters ratify the repeal of the state's prohibition law.</event>

<event start="Jun 6 1936 00:00:00 GMT 00:00:00 GMT" title="The Texas Centennial Exposition opens at Dallas' Fair Park" end="Nov 29 1936 00:00:00 GMT">June 6 – The Texas Centennial Exposition opens at Dallas' Fair Park; it runs until Nov. 29.</event>

<event start="Mar 18 1937 00:00:00 GMT" title="A massive natural gas leak explosion kills 311">March 18 – A massive explosion, blamed on a natural-gas leak beneath the London Consolidated School building in Rusk County, kills an estimated 296 students and teachers. Subsequent deaths of people injured in the explosion bring the death count to 311. As a result, the Texas legislature requires that a malodorant be added to the odorless gas so that leaks can be more easily detected.</event>

<event start="1945" title="The United States participates in World War II" end="1945 00:00:00 GMT">The United States participates in World War II.</event>

<event start="1943" title="Beaumont riots lead to martial law">June – A race riot in Beaumont leads to a declaration of martial law.</event>

<event start="Apr 16 1947 00:00:00 GMT" title="SS Grandcapmp explodes in the Texas City harbor">April 16 – The French-owned SS Grandcamp, carrying ammonium nitrate, explodes in the Texas City harbor, followed the next morning by the explosion of the SS High Flyer. The disaster kills almost 600 and injures at least 4,000 more. The concussion is felt 75 miles away in Port Arthur, and the force creates a 15-foot tidal wave.</event>

<event start="1948" title="Lyndon B. Johnson beats Coke Stevenson in the U.S. Senate race">Lyndon B. Johnson beats Coke Stevenson in the U.S. Senate race by 87 votes. The winning margin in the disputed primary is registered in Ballot Box No. 13 in Jim Wells County.</event>

<event start="Aug 24 1949 00:00:00 GMT" title="The University of Texas Medical Branch in Galveston admits its first black student">Aug. 24 – The University of Texas Medical Branch in Galveston admits its first black student.</event>

<event start="1950" title="University of Texas law school racial integration begins">The U.S. Supreme Court orders racial integration of The University of Texas law school.</event>

<event start="1953" title="Dwight D. Eisenhower becomes tPresident">Dwight D. Eisenhower becomes the first Texas-born President of the United States.</event>

<event start="May 11 1953 00:00:00 GMT" title="Tornado in Waco kills 114">May 11 – A tornado kills 114, injures 597 at Waco; 150 homes and 185 other buildings are destroyed.</event>

<event start="May 22 1953 00:00:00 GMT" title="Texans given the right to its offshore oil">May 22 – The Tidelands Bill is signed by Pres. Eisenhower, giving Texas the rights to its offshore oil.</event>

<event start="1954" title="Texas women gain the right to serve on juries">Texas women gain the right to serve on juries.</event>

<event start="Sep 12 1958 00:00:00 GMT" title="Integrated circuit tested at Texas Instruments">Sept. 12 – The integrated circuit, developed by Jack Kilby at Texas Instruments, Dallas, is successfully tested, ushering in the semiconductor and electronics age.</event>

<event start="1961" title="John Tower wins a special election for U.S. Senate">John Tower wins a special election for U.S. Senate, becoming the first Republican senator from Texas since Reconstruction.</event>

<event start="1962" title="NASA opens the Manned Spacecraft Center in Houston">NASA opens the Manned Spacecraft Center in Houston. The center moves to a new campus-like building complex in 1964. It is renamed Lyndon B. Johnson Space Center on Aug. 17, 1973.</event>

<event start="Nov 22 1963 00:00:00 GMT" title="President John F. Kennedy assassinated in Dallas">Nov. 22 – President John F. Kennedy is assassinated in Dallas; vice president Lyndon B. Johnson succeeds to the office, becoming the 36th U.S. president.</event>

<event start="1964" title="Poll tax is abolished">The poll tax is abolished by the 24th Amendment to the U.S. Constitution as a requirement for voting for federal offices. It is retained in Texas, however, for state and local offices.</event>

<event start="1965" title="Texas legislature is reapportioned">The Texas Legislature is reapportioned on the principle of one person, one vote.</event>

<event start="Jun 3 1965 00:00:00 GMT" title="Ed White becomes the first American to walk in space">June 3 – San Antonio native Ed White becomes the first American to walk in space.</event>

<event start="1966" title="Poll tax is repealed">The poll tax is repealed as a requirement for voting in all elections by amendment of the Texas Constitution.</event>

<event start="1966" title="Barbara Jordan becomes the first black woman elected to Texas Senate">Barbara Jordan of Houston becomes the first black woman elected to the Texas Senate.</event>

<event start="Aug 1 1966 00:00:00 GMT" title="Charles Whitman kills 17 people">Aug. 1 – Charles Whitman kills 17 people, shooting them from the observation deck of the main-building tower on The University of Texas campus in Austin.</event>

<event start="1967" title="Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund incorporated">The Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund (MALDEF) is incorporated in Texas; its first national office is in San Antonio.</event>

<event start="Jul 20 1969 00:00:00 GMT" title="Apollo 11 astronaut Neil Armstrong transmits the first words from the surface of the moon">July 20 – Apollo 11 astronaut Neil Armstrong transmits the first words from the surface of the moon: "Houston, the Eagle has landed."</event>

<event start="1971" title="SEC investigates illegal manipulation of stock transactions">The Securities and Exchange Commission investigates illegal manipulation of stock transactions involving Frank Sharp and his Sharpstown State Bank of Houston. The Sharpstown Scandal results in the conviction of House speaker Gus Mutscher and two associates for conspiracy and bribery in 1972.</event>

<event start="Jan 8 1974 00:00:00 GMT" title="New state constitution is attempted">Jan. 8 – A Constitutional Convention meets to attempt to write a new state constitution. However, the delegates, comprising the membership of the 63rd Legislature, become mired in divisive politics, and the convention adjourns on July 30, 1974, without a document.</event>

<event start="1978" title="Clements becomes first Republican governor of Texas since Reconstruction">William Clements becomes the first Republican governor of Texas since Reconstruction.</event>

<event start="Apr 10 1979 00:00:00 GMT" title="Several tornadoes kill 53 in West Texas">April 10 – Several tornadoes kill 53 in West Texas, including 42 in Wichita Falls, and cause $400 million in damages.</event>

<event start="1985" title="No-pass-no-play rul enacted by Texas Legislature">The no-pass-no-play rule is part of an education-reform package enacted by the Texas Legislature.</event>

<event start="Aug 20 1984 00:00:00 GMT 00:00:00 GMT" title="The National Republican Convention is held in Dallas" end="Aug 23 1984 00:00:00 GMT">Aug. 20-23 – The National Republican Convention is held in Dallas.</event>

<event start="1985" title="Insider abuse detected by the Federal Home Loan Bank Board">The Federal Home Loan Bank Board suspends deposit insurance for Texas savings-and-loan companies applying for state charters. Three years later, after uncovering widespread insider abuse at Texas lending institutions, federal regulators announce bail-out plans for many Texas thrifts and begin prosecution of S&amp;L officials.</event>

<event start="1988" title="George Bush elected President">Houstonian George Bush is elected president of the United States.</event>

<event start="1990 00:00:00 GMT" title="Ann Richards becomes first woman governor of Texas" end="Ann Richards becomes first woman governor of Texas 00:00:00 GMT">Democrat Ann Richards becomes the first woman governor of Texas in her own right.</event>

<event start="Apr 19 1993 00:00:00 GMT" title="86 Branch Davidians and 4 federal agents killed in Waco siege">April 19 – Ending a siege that began on Feb. 28, federal agents storm the compound called Mount Carmel near Waco, where cult leader David Koresh and his followers, called Branch Davidians, had reportedly been storing a large cache of assault weapons. The assault and ensuing fire kill four agents and 86 Branch Davidians.</event>

<event start="1993" title="Republican Kay Bailey Hutchison becomes first Texan woman Senator">Republican Kay Bailey Hutchison becomes the first woman to serve as U.S. Senator from Texas.</event>

<event start="2000" title="George W. Bush elected President">Former Texas Gov. George W. Bush is elected President of the United States.</event>
</data>